本节中，我们构建两个经典的MAC：CBC-MAC
In this segment, we're going to construct
two classic MACs, the CBC-MAC and the
和NMAC。在上一节中，我们说过
如果给我一个安全的PRF
NMAC. Recall in the last segment, we said
that if you give me a secure PRF, then
那么安全的PRF可以被用来构建一个安全的MAC
that secure PRF can actually be used to
construct a secure MAC, simply by defining
定义信息M的签名为函数在点M处的值
the signature on the message M as the
value of the function at the point M. The
唯一的警告是，PRF F的输出必须要大。比如
only caveat was that the output of the
PRF F had to be large. For example, it
可以是80位或128位，可以生成一个安全MAC
could be 80 bits or 128 bits, and that
would generate a secure MAC. Now we also
我们说过，因为AES是一个安全的PRF，
AES已经给了我们一个安全的MAC
said that because AES is a secure PRF,
essentially AES already gives us a secure
但是它只能处理16字节的信息
MAC, except that it can only process
sixteen byte messages. And the question
现在问题是，给定一个处理短信息的PRF
比如AES可以处理16字节信息
now is, given a PRF for short messages
like AES for sixteen byte messages, can we
我们能不能构建一个PRF来处理长信息
比如几个G的信息呢？
construct a PRF for long messages that are
potentially gigabytes long? And this is
这就是下面所述的来历。我记为X，即｛0,1｝^N
shorthand for what's coming. I'm going to
denote by X, the set ｛0,1｝ to the N where N
这里N是底层PRF的分组大小
因为我们总是拿AES作为底层的PRF
is the block size for the underlying PRF.
So since we're always going to be thinking
你可以把N当成128位
of AES as the underlying PRF, you can
think of N as essentially 128 bits. So
第一个机制叫做加密的CBC-MAC，或简记为ECBC
the first construction is called the
encrypted CBC MAC, or ECBC for short.
加密的CBC-MAC。那么ECBC使用一个PRF
输入集合X=｛0,1｝^N中的信息
Encrypted CBC MAC. So ECBC uses a PRF that
takes messages in the set X ｛0,1｝ to the N
输出同样的集合X中的信息。我们要构建一个PRF
and outputs messages in the same set X.
And what we're going to be building is a
取一对密钥。它去很长的信息
PRF that basically takes pairs of keys. It
takes very long messages, in fact
事实上是任意长的信息，我稍后再解释这点
arbitrarily long messages, and I'll
explain this in just a second and it
它输出｛0,1｝^N中的标签。这是我们的目标。
那这个|X|的不大于L次方是什么意思？
outputs also tags in ｛0,1｝ to the N. So
that's our goal. Now what is this X to the
这里是说，CBC-MAC可以取最多长L个分组的信息
less than or equal to L? The point here is
that in fact CBC MAC can take very long
L可以是百万或十亿的大小
messages up to L blocks. L could be a
million or a billion. But it could also
它还可以是变化的输入信息的长度
换句话说，|X|不大于L
take variable length messages as inputs.
In other words, X less than or equal to L
意思是我们允许输入的信息包含的分组数
means that we allow the input to be
messages that contain an arbitrary number
可以是从0到L的任一数。每个CBC可以处理
一个分组长的信息
of blocks between one and L. So each CBC
can process messages that are one block
两个分组长的、十个分组长的、100个分组长的信息
long, two blocks long, ten blocks long,
100 blocks long. It's perfectly fine to
给可变长度的输入是完全可以的。为了讨论方便
give it variable size inputs. But just to
keep the discussion simple, we up our
我们把最大信息长度界定为L。那我们来看ECBC如何工作
bounds the maximum length by capital L. So
let's see how ECBC works. Well, we start
我们一开始取信息，把它分割成一个个的分组
by taking our message and breaking it into
blocks, each block is as long as a block
每个分组和底层函数f的分组一样长
然后我们沿着CBC链接运行
of the underlying function f, and then
essentially we run through the CBC chain
但不输出中间值。大家注意
except that we don't output intermediate
values. So you notice we basically encrypt
我们加密第一个分组，然后把结果与第二个分组异或
the first block and then feed the results
into the XOR with the second block and
再把结果交给f，一次又一次地这样做
then feed that into f again, and we do
that again and again and again and finally
最后我们得到了一个值，叫做这个长长的链接的CBC输出
we get a value out here. Which is called
the CBC outputs of this long chain. And
那么，我想让大家注意一个事实
那就是我们要多做一步加密
then, I would like to point your attention
to the fact that we do one more encryption
这一步使用一个独立的密钥来完成
step. And this step is actually done using
an independent key, K1. That's different
这个密钥是独立选择的，与密钥K不同
最后的输出结果就是我们所求的标签
and chosen independently of the key K, and
finally the output gives us the tag. So in
在这种情况下，标签为N位长。
但我们在之前一节中提过
this case the tag would be N bits long,
but we also mentioned in the previous
我们是可以截断标签的，使之长度小于N
segment that it's fine to truncate the tag
to less than N bits long as long as one
只要1除以2的长度次方是可忽略的
现在大家看到ECBC取一对密钥作为输入
over two to the end is negligible. So now
you can see that ECBC takes a pair of
它可以处理可变长的信息
keys as inputs, it can process
variable length messages and it produces
它的输出在集合X中。大家可能想知道
最后一步的加密是干什么的？
an output in the set X. So you might be
wondering what this last encryption step
我告诉大家，不定义最后一步加密的函数
is for. And I'll tell you that the
function that's defined without this last
叫做原CBC函数。换句话说
encryption step is called the raw CBC
function. In other words, if we simply
如果我们就在这里停止处理了，
我们得到的输出，叫做原CBC
stop processing over here, and we take
that as the output, that's called raw CBC.
我们待会会看到，原CBC并不是一个安全的MAC
And as we'll see in a minute, raw CBC is
actually not a secure MAC. So this last
最后一步对于MAC的安全性是很重要的
step is actually critical for making
the MAC secure. So another class of
另一类构建机制，将小PRF转变成大PRF的，
叫做NMAC
construction for converting a small PRF
into a large PRF is called NMAC,
嵌套MAC。NMAC从PRF开始，与之前一样
for Nested MAC. Now, the NMAC starts
from PRF that, as before, takes inputs
取X中的输入，输出密钥空间里的元素。记得在CBC里
in X, but outputs elements in the key
space. And remember that for CBC, the
输出一定在集合X里。这里，输出需要在密钥空间K里
output has to be in the set X. Here, the
output needs to be in the key space K. And
我们获得了这个PRF F_NMAC，它取一对密钥作为输入
again, we basically obtain the PRF F_NMAC, which takes pairs of keys as inputs.
它还可以处理变长的信息，最多L个分组
Again, can process variable length
messages up until L blocks. And the output
输出是密钥空间中的一个元素
NMAC工作的方式，开头和之前一样
is an element in the key space. And the
way NMAC works is kind of, starts as
我们取我们的信息，把它分成若干分组
before. We take our message, and we break
it into blocks. Each block is, again, as
每个分组的长度与底层PRF的分组长度一致。
现在我们取我们的密钥
big as the block length of the underlying
PRF. And now we take our key and we feed
把我们的密钥交给函数F，信息分组
our key as the key input into the function
F. And the message block is given as the
也是作为数据输入给函数F。得到的结果
就作为NMAC的下一个分组的密钥
data input into the function F. What comes
out is the key for the next block of NMAC.
现在我们为下一次PRF的计算，有了一个新的密钥
So now we have a new key for the next
evaluation of the PRF. And the data for
下一次计算的数据是下一个信息分组，等等
the next evaluation is the next message
block and so on and so forth until we
知道我们到达最后的输出。最后的输出
是K中的元素，对吧？
reach the final output. The final output
is gonna be an element in K. Okay? And
与之前一样，事实上，如果我们停在这里
我们得到的函数叫做
just as before, in fact, if we stop here.
The function that we obtain is called a
级联函数。我们待会会看到级联的更多细节
cascade function. And we're gonna look at
cascade in more detail in just a minute.
级联会输出K中的一个元素。但是，我们还会看到
So cascade will output an element in K.
However, that, as we'll see again, is not
级联不是安全的MAC。为了获得一个安全的MAC
我们需要把这个K中的元素T
a secure MAC. To get a secure MAC, what we
do is we need to map this element T,
映射到集合X中。典型地，我们会看到
which is in K, into the set X. And so,
typically, as we'll see, NMAC is used
NMAC用到的PRF的分组长度|X|远远大于密钥长度
with, PRFs, where the block length, X, is
much bigger than the key length. And so
我们就把固定的补齐附在信息后面
fpad是固定的补齐
what we do is we simply append fixed pad.
fpad is called a fixed pad that gets
附在这个标签T后面。然后这里的输入
appended to this tag T. And then this
becomes, this input here, this block here
这个分组成为了X中的一个元素。我们把这个分组
交给函数，同时还注意到这里
becomes an element of X. We feed this into
the function, and again, notice here that
最后一步加密使用了一个独立的密钥
there's an independent key that's being
used for the last encryption step. And
最后一个标签是K中的一个元素，我们输出它
then finally, the last tag is an element
of K which we output as the output of
作为NMAC的输出。记住如果没有最后一步加密
NMAC. So remember without the last
encryption step, the function is called a
这个函数叫做级联。带这最后一步，
我们会看到它对安全性来说是必须的
cascade. With the last step as we'll see
which is necessary for security, we
我们有一个PRF，输出K中的元素，可以处理
actually get a PRF which outputs elements
in K, and can process variable length
可变长信息，最多L个分组长。好，这就是NMAC
messages that are up to L blocks long.
Alright so that is the NMAC
那么我们有了两个MAC。根据AES
我们可以构建一个大PRF
construction. So now we have two MACs. That
we can use to build a large PRF, from AES,
在我分析MAC机制的安全性之前
basically. So before I analyze the
security of MAC constructions, I'd like
我想让大家更好地理解最后一步的意义
you to understand better what the last
encryption step is for. So, let's start
那么我们从NMAC开始。我已解释了
非常容易看出，如果我们忽略了
with NMAC. So I explained that it
is actually very easy to see that if we
最后一步加密，换句话说，如果我们使用级联函数
omitted the last encryption step. In other
words, if we just use the cascade
那么这个MAC将是完全不安全的。假如我们看
function, then the MAC will be completely
insecure. Okay so suppose we look at this
这里的MAC，换句话说，我们直接输出
MAC to find over here. In other words, all
we do is we output directly the cascade
M的级联函数结果，不做最后一步加密
我问大家如何伪造这个MAC里的标签？
applied to M without the last encryption
step. So let me ask you how do you forge
我猜我已经把错误答案给出了
tags in this MAC. And I guess I've kinda
given it away that this answer isn't
我希望大家能看出答案是，给定一个
correct. So I hope everybody sees that the
answer is, that, in fact, given one chosen
选择信息的询问，你就可以实施一次存在性伪造了
message query, you can mount an
existential forgery. And the reason is,
我会以图表的形式为大家展示其原因
让我先把它以符号形式写在这
I'll show you in a second in the diagram,
but let me write it out in symbols first.
原因是，如果有了级联函数在信息M处的输出
The reason if, if you're given the output
of the cascade function applied to a
我作为攻击者，就可以根据这个输出推导出
message M. I can derive from it, me being
the adversary, I can derive from it the
级联函数在信息M联结上W的值，这里W可以是任意信息
cascade applied to the message M
concatenated W for any message W, for any
首先，应当清楚这对于实施存在性伪造
W. So first of all, it should be clear
that this is enough to mount an
是足够的，因为通过询问这个信息的标签
existential forgery because essentially by
asking for a tag on this message I obtain
我获得了这个更长的信息的标签
我就可以输出它作为我的伪造，好
the tag on this longer message which I can
then output as my forgery. Okay, so the
那么MAC是不安全的，因为给定了一个信息的MAC
我可以产生另一个信息的MAC
MAC is insecure because given a MAC in one
message, I can produce the MAC in another
但是让我们回到之前描述的级联函数的图
来看看为什么这是正确的
message. But let's go back to the diagram
describing cascade, and see why this is
让我们看看如果这最后一步不在的话，会发生什么
true. And so let's see what happens if
this last step isn't there. As an
作为一个攻击者，我能再加一个分组在这，记之为W
attacker, what I can do, I can add one
more block here, which we called W. And
然后我可以取级联函数的输出，也就是值T
then, then basically, I can take the
output of cascade, which is this value T.
然后应用函数F来计算T，这里我取这个T值
And we can simply apply the function F to
it again. So here I'll take this T value.
我把它带入到F里，带入我的最后一个分组W
I'll plug it in to F. And plug my last
block W into it and what I'll get is T
我会得到T'，也就是级联函数在信息M联结W的值
prime which is, well, the evaluation of
cascade on the message M concatenated W.
我可以使用我们计算的T'来进行存在性伪造
In our calculated T prime, which I can use
for my existential forgery. Okay, so this
这就证明了为什么级联的这个性质成立
这个叫做扩展攻击
kind of shows you why this property of
cascade holds. This is called an extension
给定信息M的标签，我可以推出M的扩展信息的标签
attack, where giving a tag of the message
m I can deduce the tag for the extension
事实上对任何我选择的扩展
of m. And in fact for any extension of my
choice. So basically, cascade is
级联都是完全不安全的，如果我们不做最后一步加密的话
completely insecure if we don't do this
last encryption step, and the last
这里最后一步加密阻止了这种扩展攻击
encryption step here basically prevents
this type of extension attack. I can tell
我可以顺便告诉大家，事实上扩展攻击是
针对级联的唯一一种攻击
you by the way that in fact extension
attacks are the only attacks on a cascade
可以说得更清楚些，但我这里就不说了
and that could be made precise. But I'm
not gonna do that here. The next question
下一个问题是，在这个ECBC机制中，我们
为什么要有多出来的这个加密分组？
is, why did we have the extra encryption
block in the ECBC construction? So again,
让我告诉大家，如果没有这个多出来的加密分组
ECBC将是不安全的
let me show you that without this extra
encryption block ECBC is insecure. So
我们定义一个使用原CBC的映射
换句话说，它和CBC-MAC是一样的
let's define a map that uses raw CBC. In
other words, it's the same as CBC MAC, but
但没有最后一步加密。我们看到这个MAC也是不安全的
without the last encryption step. And
let's see that, that MAC is also insecure.
不过这个攻击比简单的扩展攻击更困难点
Except now, the attack is a little bit
more difficult than a simple extension
假设攻击者有了这个值，原CBC在特定信息M处的值
attack. So suppose the attacker is given
this value, the raw CBC value for a
现在，攻击者想扩展和计算某个信息
particular message M. And now, the
attacker wants to extend and compute the
再联结上某个字W的MAC。这是我们的W
MAC on some message M, concatenated on
with some word W. So here's our W well the
攻击者可以取这个值，试着将两者进行异或
core attacker can take this value and try
to XOR the two together but now you
大家发现他必须计算这个函数
这里，攻击者不知道
realize he has to evaluate the function.
At this point. But he doesn't know what
这个密钥K是什么。因此，他不知道这个函数的输出
this key K is. And as a result, he doesn't
know what the output of the function is.
他不能仅根据分组W就计算出原CBC
So he simply can't just depend on
block W, and compute the value of
在N联结W处的值。不过，其实他可以计算
raw CBC on N concatenated W. However, it
turns out they he can actually evaluate
这个函数。通过选择信息攻击。我想告诉大家
this function. By using the chosen message
attack. And I wanna show you how to do
怎么去做。好，我们说过我们的目标是
证明原CBC是不安全的
that. Okay, so we said that basically so
our goal is to show raw CBC is insecure.
我们看一个特殊的攻击，在这个攻击里
So let's look at a particular attack. So
in the attack, the adversary is going to
攻击者先请求一个特定信息M的标签
信息M只有一个分组长
start by requesting the tag on a
particular message m that's a one-block
对一个单分组信息应用CBC意味着什么？
message. So what does it mean to apply CBC
to a one-block message? Well basically,
你只需直接应用函数f。那么你获得了这个标签
all you do is you just apply the function
f directly. So what you get is the tag,
即直接应用f在单分组信息M处的结果
which is just the application of f
directly to the one-block message m. Good,
现在攻击者有了这个值T
现在我声称他可以定义这个信息M'
so now the adversary has this value T. And
now I claim that he can define this
包含两个分组，第一个是M
message, M prime, which contains two
blocks. The first block is M, the second
第二个是T异或M。我声称，刚刚收到的值T
block is T XOR M. And I claim that the
value T that he just received is a valid
是这两个分组的信息M'的标签。
我们看为什么这是对的
tag for this two block message, M Prime.
So let's see why that's true. Well, so
假设我们在这个信息M'上应用原CBC
suppose we apply the raw CBC construction
to this message M prime. So if you plug it
如果你把它带入，我们看，这应该能成功。首先
in directly what, let's see. The way it
would work is first of all, the first
第一个信息M被加密处理，直接使用函数F
message M is processed by encrypting it
directly using the function F. Then we XOR
然后我们把结果和第二个分组异或，
就是T异或M，然后我们对结果应用F
the results with the second block
with is T-XOR-M. And then we apply F to
这是原CBC的定义。关于F(k,m)我们知道什么？
the results of that. That is the
definition of raw CBC. Now what do we know about
根据定义，F(k,m)就是T。那么下一步里
F(k,m)? F(k,m) is simply this value T by
definition. So the next step we get is
我们获得T异或T异或M，但T异或T相抵消了
essentially T-XOR-T-XOR-M. But
this T- XOR-T simply goes away and what
所以我们得到的就是F(k,m)。当然就是T了
因此T是这个两分组信息(M,T异或M)的有效MAC
we get is F(k,m). Which is, of course, T.
And as a result, T is a valid MAC for the
攻击者可以产生这个有效的标签T
two block message, (M, T-XOR-M). So
the adversary was able to produce this
而这个两分组的信息是从未被询问过的
valid tag T for this two block message
that he never queried. And therefore, he
因此，他可以破解这个MAC了。我们再看一眼这个ECBC图
was able to break the MAC. So let's look
at the ECBC diagram for just one more
我指出，如果计算MAC时，不包含最后一步加密的话
second. And let me point out that if you
don't include this last encryption step in
MAC将是不安全的
the computation of the MAC, essentially,
the MAC would be insecure because of the
因为我们刚刚看到的攻击。我要告诉大家
有很多产品也犯了这样的错误
attack that we just saw. And I'll tell you
that there are many products that do this
事实上，有些标准也做得不对
incorrectly. And, in fact, there are even
standards that do this incorrectly, so
得到的MAC是不安全的。大家现在知道了这步是需要做的
that the resulting MAC is insecure. You
now know that this needs to be done, and
大家自己别犯这个错误了。那么
我们看一下CBC和NMAC的
you won't make this mistake yourself. So
let's state the CBC and NMAC security
安全性定理。通常，命题是针对任意长度的信息
theorems. And so the statement is as usual
for any message length that we'd like to,
应用MAC。对任意攻击PRF的攻击者A
apply the MAC to. Essentially for every
PRF adversary A, there's an efficient
都存在一个有效的攻击者B，这些表述一般命题里都有
adversary B and, you know, these are kind
of the usual statements. Where, the facts
大家需要知道这里的误差项，两种情况的误差项很相似
that you need to know are the error terms
which are kind of similar in both cases.
顺便一提，我想指出这里对CBC的分析
By the way, I'd like to point out that the
analysis for CBC actually uses the fact
使用了F是PRP这一事实，尽管我们从来没有
在ECBC的计算中，求F的逆
that F is a PRP even though we never had
to invert F during the computation of
如果假设F是PRP，这个分析会更好。换句话说
ECBC, the analysis is better if you assume
that F is actually a PRP. In other words,
F是可逆的，不仅仅是一个函数而已
对于一个MAC，PRF不一定是可逆的
it's invertible, not just a function. For
a MAC, the PRF need not be invertible.
这些误差项告诉我们，这些MAC是安全的
So what these error terms basically say
is that these MACs are secure, as long as,
只要用于计算MAC的密钥使用次数不超过|X|的平方根
也不超过K的平方根
key is not used to MAC more than square
root of X or square root of K messages. So
对于AES来说，这当然就是2的64次方了
我想给大家一个例子
for AES of course this would be a two to
the 64. But I want to show you an example
来展示如何使用这些上界。这里我又写下了
CBC-MAC的安全性定理
of how you would use these bounds. So
here, I've stated the security theorem again
这里的q是询问的信息数，并用一特定密钥计算MAC
for the CBC MAC, and Q here, again, is the
number of messages that are MACed with a
假设我们想确保所有的攻击者
particular key. So suppose we wanted to
ensure that for all adversaries that the
区分PRF和真随机函数的优势都小于1除以2的32次方
adversary has an advantage of less than
one over two to the 32 in distinguishing
假设这是我们的目标
the PRF from a truly random function.
Suppose that is our goal. Well, by the
根据安全性定理，这意味着我们需要确保
security theorem, what that means is we
need to ensure that Q squared over X is
q^2/|X|小于1除以2的32次方。
我们希望这一项。。
less than one over two to the 32, right.
We want this term to be, well, I'm going
我想忽略这个2，以求简便。
我们想确保这一项
to ignore this two here just for
simplicity. We want to ensure this term is
小于1除以2的32次方，那么这一项当然就是可忽略的
less than one over two to the 32 and this
term, of course, is negligible, so we can
这样我们就可以忽略之。这意味着
这一项也小于1除以2的32次方
just ignore it. This would imply that this
term is also less than one over two to the
好，如果我们想确保优势小于1除以2的32次方
32. Okay, so if we want to ensure that the
advantage is less than one over two to the
我们需要确保q^2/|X|小于1除以2的32次方
32, we need to ensure that Q squared over
X is less than one over two to the 32. For
对于AES，这意味着计算了2的48次方个信息的MAC后
AES, basically this means that after MACing
two to the 48 messages, you have to
你就必须更换密钥了。否则，MAC就不安全了
change your key. Otherwise, you won't
achieve the security level. So you can
所以你只能最多计算2的48次方个信息的MAC。
注意到如果我带入3DES的参数
MAC, at most, two to the 48 messages. You
notice that if I plug in triple DES, which
3DES分组更短，只有64位。同样的计算告诉我们
has a much shorter block, only 64 bits.
The same result says you now have to
必须每65000个信息就更换密钥
因此这就很有问题了
change your key every 65,000 messages. So
this basically is quite problematic
而这个AES还是可以的。这是个非常大的数
whereas this is fine. This is actually a,
a very fairly large number. For
对于AES，这意味着你必须每160亿个信息更换密钥
AES this means you have to change
your key only every 16 billion
这还是非常合理的。这也是为什么
messages which is perfectly reasonable.
And so this is one of the reasons why AES
AES有比3DES更大的分组的原因之一
有些模式依然是安全的
has a larger block, than triple DES. Some of these modes remain
大家不一定要像3DES那样频繁地更换密钥
secure and you don't have to change your
key as often as you would with triple
好，我想告诉大家，事实上这些攻击不仅在
DES. Okay, so I want to show you
that in fact these attacks are not just in
安全性定理中的命题里，它们还是真实的攻击
the statements in the security theorem, in
fact there really are real attacks that
对应于这些值。现在这些MAC值确实变得不安全了
correspond to these values. Now the MACs
really do become insecure after you sign,
在你签名了|X|或|K|的平方根个信息后。
you know, square root of X or square root
of K messages. So I'm going to show you an
那么我要告诉大家一个针对PRF的攻击，
也就是同时针对ECBC和NMAC的攻击
attack on both PRFs so either ECBC or
NMAC. Assuming that the underlying
假设底层函数是PRP，是类似AES的分组密码，我们记为F
function is a PRP, is actually a block
cipher like AES. Let's call F big, let's
我们说F可以是F_ECBC或F_NMAC
那么F意味着这是一个针对长信息的PRF
say that F big is either F ECBC or F NMAC.
So F big means that it's a PRF for large
现在，实际上两种机制都有如下的扩展性质
messages. Now, it turns out both
constructions have the following extension
如果给我一个碰撞，发生在信息X和Y上
property. Namely, if you give me a
collision. On messages X and Y. Then, in
那么事实上，这也意味着有一个碰撞发生在
X和Y的扩展上，换句话说
fact, that also implies a collision on an
extension of X and Y. In other words, if I
如果我把W各附在X和Y的后面，我也会在这些信息上
获得一个碰撞。那么
append W to both X and Y, I'll also get a
collision on the resulting words. So it's
很容易说服自己，这个扩展性质是成立的
fairly easy to convince yourself that this
extension property holds, you do it just
只需盯着这张图看一会，就能想象，我给你两个信息
by staring at the diagram for a second.
And so imagine I give you two messages
它们正好在这点发生膨胀。记得我假设F是PRP
that happen to collide at this point. Now
remember, I assumed that F is a PRP. So
那么一旦固定K1，它就是一一映射的函数
于是如果两个信息正好
once you fix K1, it's a one to one
function. So if the two messages happen to
被映射到输出的同一个值，这就意味着它们
也正好被映射到同样的值
map to the same value at the output. This
means they also happen to map to the same
作为原CBC的输出。但如果它们在原CBC的输出中
value at the output of the raw CBC
function. But if they map to the same
被映射到同样的值，这意味着如果我加上另外一个分组
value at the output of the raw CBC
function, that means that if I add another
我们记为W。我获得了这个输出。然后我们计算
block, let's call it a W. And I take this
output here. Then I'm computing the same
这两个信息的共同的函数值。对两个信息，我都会
在这个点得到同样的值
value for both messages. And I'll get, for
both messages, I'll get the same value at
当我用K1加密时，我会获得。。
this point, too. And when I encrypt,
again, with K1, I'll also get, you know,
这里还有个F。我会获得同样的输出，即最终输出
so there's one more F here. I'll also get
the same output, final output, after I've
在我附上分组W后。那么如果两个不同信息的
两个值正好是一样的
appended the block W. Okay, so if the two
values happen to be the same for two
如果我附上分组W到两个信息后面，我依然能获得
distinct messages. If I appended block W
to both messages, I'm still gonna get the
同样的输出值。容易说服自己，这一点对NMAC也成立
same value out. It's easy to convince
yourself that the same is true for NMAC
这两个PRF都有这个扩展性质成立。基于此
as well. Okay, so both of these, PRFs have
this extension property. So based on this,
我们可以定义一个攻击。这是扩展性质的描述
we can define an attack. So here's the
extension property stated again. And the
攻击如下工作。假设我发出了|Y|的平方根个
attack would work as follows. Suppose I
issued square of Y chosen message
选择信息的询问。对于AES，Y是｛0,1｝^128
queries. So, for AES, remember, the value
of Y is basically ｛0,1｝ to the 128. So this
这意味着我要问2的64次方个信息的询问
would mean that I would be asking, two to
the 64 shows in message queries for just
询问输入空间中的任意信息的标签
arbitrary messages in the input space.
Well, what will happen is, I'll obtain,
我会获得2的64次方个信息-MAC对。在下一章中
well, I'll obtain two to the 64 message
MAC pairs. Now, we're gonna see in the
我们将看到，有一个叫做生日悖论的
next module, actually, there's something
called a birthday paradox. Some of you may
有人可能已经听说过了。它告诉我们
如果我有2的128次方大小的空间里的
have heard of it already. It basically
says that if I have two to the 64 random
2的64次方个随机元素，有很大的几率
elements of a space of size two to the
128, there's a good chance that two of
其中有两个元素是相同的。
那么我看两个不同的信息，MU和MV
them are the same. So I'm gonna look for
two distinct messages. MU and MV, for
两个的对应MAC是一样的。我说过
which the corresponding MACs are the same.
Okay, and as I said, by the birthday
根据生日悖论，这些极有可能存在。
一旦我有了它们
paradox, these are very likely to exist.
Once I have that, now I've basically found
我就发现了MU和MV，它们有着同样的MAC
因此，我可以用任一字W来扩展MU
MU and MV to have the same MAC. And as a
result, what I can do is, I can extend MU
然后询问MU联结W后的标签
with an arbitrary word W, and ask for the
tag for the word MU concatenated W. But
但因为MU和MV有着同样的输出
because MU and MV happen to have the same
output, I know that MU concatenated W has
MU||W与MV||W的输出也是相同的。
所有现在我获得了MU||W的输出
the same output as MV concatenated W. So
now that I've obtained the output for MU
也就是获得了MV||W的输出
concatenated W, I also have the output for
MV concatenated W. And therefore I have
因此，我获得了我的伪造方法。现在T也是
一个信息MV||W的伪造
obtained my forgery. Okay, so now T is
also a forgery for the message MV
而这个信息我们之前从没问过
因此，这是一个有效的可能伪造
concatenated W which I've never asked
before. And therefore, this is as valid as
好，这是一个犀利的攻击，最保守的说
a potential forgery. Okay, so this is kind
of an acute attack and the bottom line
事实上经过|Y|的平方根个询问后，我可以伪造一个MAC
here is that in fact after square root of
Y queries, I am able to forge a MAC with
以很高的概率成功。好，那么|Y|的平方根意味着什么？
fairly good probability. Okay, so what
does square root of Y mean? If we go back
如果我们回到安全性定理，这意味着对于ECBC，
经过|X|的平方根个信息
to the security theorems, this means that
basically for ECBC after square root of X
或是对于NMAC，经过|K|的平方根个信息，
计算过这么多信息的MAC后
or for NMAC after square root of K,
messages have been MACed, the MAC becomes
MAC将变得不安全了，攻击者可以为新信息找到新的MAC
insecure and the attacker can actually
find new MACs for messages for which he
而这些新信息的MAC攻击者之前从未听过
这是一个犀利的攻击
was never given a MAC for. So again, this
is an acute attack that shows the bounds
证实了定理的上界是真实的
因此这个例子中推出的上界
of the theorem really are real. And as a
result these bounds that derived in this
是真实的，大家不应当使用单个密钥计算超过
example are real and you should never use
a single key to MAC more than, say, two
2的48次方个信息，使用基于AES的CBC。
总结一下，我们已经看了两个例子
to 48 messages with AES based CBC. So to
conclude, I'll just mention that we've
ECBC和NMAC。ECBC事实上是非常常见的MAC
seen two examples. We saw ECBC and NMAC.
ECBC is in fact, a very commonly used MAC
根据AES构建的，例如802.11i使用AES的ECBC
来保护数据完整性
that's built from AES. 802.11i, for example,
uses ECBC with AES for integrity.
有一个NIST标准叫做CMAC，我们下一节讨论它
There's also a NIST standard called CMAC,
that we'll talk in the next segment, that
它也是基于ECBC MAC的。而NMAC不常与分组密码
also is based on the ECBC MAC. NMAC with
contrast is not typically used with a
配合使用，主要原因是在NMAC机制里
block cipher. And the main reason is, you know
that in the NMAC construction,
各个分组的密钥会变化。这意味着整个AES密钥扩展
the key changes from block to block. That
means that the whole AES key expansion has
对每个分组都必须重新计算，而在这里AES并不是能
to be computed and recomputed on every
block. And AES is not designed to perform
表现很好，当密钥快速变化时。
当你使用NMAC时
well when he changes key very rapidly. And
so, typically, when you use NMAC, you use
可以使用更善于处理各个分支上变化密钥的分组密码
block ciphers that are better at changing
their keys on every block. And as a
因此NMAC一般不用AES。事实上
result, NMAC typically is not used with
AES. But in fact, NMAC is a basis of a
NMAC是一个非常流行的MAC叫HMAC的基础
我们稍后将看到HMAC
very popular MAC called HMAC, which we're
also gonna look at next. And you'll see
大家会清楚地看到，NMAC在HMAC的底层工作
very clearly, the NMAC underlying the HMAC construction. Okay, so that's the end
本节完结，下节我们讨论MAC的更多内容
of this segment, and we'll talk about more
MACs in the next segment.